<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<TEI>
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>2.Cor.5.19. God was in Christ Reconciling the World to Himself</title>
                
                <author>
                    <trait type="gender"><desc>Female</desc></trait>
                    <forename>Katherine</forename>
                    <surname>Philips</surname>
                    <date when="1632-01-01">Birth: 1632 January 1</date>
                    <date when="1664-06-22">Death: 1664 June 22</date>           
                    <roleName>Poet</roleName>
                    <affiliation>Married</affiliation>
                    <country>Great Britain</country>
                </author>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription, correction, editorial commentary, and markup</resp>
                    <name>Staff and Research Assistants at The University of Virginia</name>
                    <name>John O'Brien</name>
                    <name>Sara Brunstetter</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Literature in Context</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <orgName>Literature in context</orgName>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>University of Virginia Department of English</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>P. O. Box 400121</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Charlottesville, VA </addrLine>
                        <addrLine>22904-4121</addrLine>
                    </address>
                    <email>jobrien@virginia.edu</email>
                </distributor>
                <authority>
                    <idno>Philips-To</idno>
                </authority>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"> Published by Literature in Context under a Creative Commons                             Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 Unported License</licence>
                    <p>While free, this text is still incomplete and requires standardization of its annotation scheme.</p>
                </availability>
                <date>2018</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>Write source here
                    <extent></extent>
                </bibl>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>
                            <persName type="lastFirst" key="philipsKatherine">Katherine Philips</persName>
                        </author>
                        <title type="main">2.Cor.5.19. God was in Christ Reconciling the World to Himself</title>
                        
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>
                                <placeName type="country" key="eng">England</placeName>
                            </pubPlace>
                            <publisher>original publisher</publisher>
                            <date when="1000-10-10">date published</date>
                        </imprint>                    
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>    
            </sourceDesc>        
        </fileDesc>
        
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc> <p>
                This text is prepared as part of the <hi>Literature in Context</hi> project, which provides an accessible, curated, edited, and marked-up selection of primary sources relevant to the study and the teaching of British and American literature of the 17th, 18th, and 19th centuries. This project is funded by the National Endowment for the Humanities and developed by faculty at The University of Virginia and Marymount University.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <interpretation><p>Research informing these annotations draws on publicly-accessible resources, with links provided where possible. Annotations have also included common knowledge, defined as information that can be found in multiple reliable sources. If you notice an error in these annotations, please contact lic.open.anthology@gmail.com.</p>
                </interpretation>
                <normalization><p>Original spelling and capitalization is retained, though the long s has been silently modernized and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p></normalization>
                <hyphenation><p>Hyphenation has not been retained, except where necessary for the sense of the word.</p></hyphenation>
                <segmentation><p>Page breaks have been retained. Catchwords, signatures, and running headers have not.</p></segmentation>
                <correction><p>Materials have been transcribed from and checked against first editions, where possible. See the Sources section.</p></correction>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="ToBeDetermined">
                    <bibl></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>        
        <body>           
             <div>                         
                <head><ref target="a001" corresp="n001">2.Cor.5.19.</ref><note xml:id="a001" target="n001">2.Cor.5.19. in the Christian Bible is the verse "that God was reconciling the world to himself in Christ, not counting peopleís sins against them. And he has committed to us the message of reconciliation" (English Standard Version. Bible Gateway)</note> God was in Christ Reconciling the World to Himself</head>
                <author>Katherine Philips</author>
                    
                    <lg type="stanza">
                        <l>When God, <ref target="a002" corresp="n002">contracted</ref> <note xml:id="n002" target="a002">a "contract", indicating a formal obligation</note>to Humanity,</l> 
                        <l>Could sigh and suffer, could be sick and die;</l>
                        <l>When all the heap of Miracles combin'd</l>
                        <l>To form the greatest, which was, <ref target="a003" corresp="n003">save Mankind</ref><note xml:id="n003" target="a003">Saving Mankind as being the "greatest Miracle", indicating authorial commentary on the state on mankind</note>:</l> 
                        <l>Then God took stand in Christ, studying a way</l>
                        <l>How to repair the Ruin'd World's <ref target="a004" corresp="n004">decay</ref><note xml:id="n004" target="a004">again, the authorial language -- "decay", indicating something that was once new has now rotted; a loss of quality</note>.</l> 
                        <l>His Love, Pow'r, Wisdom, must some mean procure</l>
                        <l>His Mercy to advance, Justice secure:</l>
                        <l>And since Man in Misery was <ref target="a006" corresp="n006">hurl'd</ref><note xml:id="n006" target="a006">"hurl'd" suggests forceful, nonwilling movement-- a potential reference to Adam and Eve ("Man") being hurled from the Garden of Eden into the world ("Misery")</note>,</l> 
                        <l>It cost him more to save then make the World.</l> 
                        <l>Oh! what a desp'rate load of sins had <ref target="a007" corresp="n007">we</ref><note xml:id="n007" target="a007">"We" -- speaker is not passive, but rather identifies as part of humanity</note>,</l> 
                        <l>When God must plot for our Felicity?</l> 
                        <l>When <ref target="a008" corresp="n008">God must beg us</ref><note xml:id="n008" target="a008">Relationship dynamic of humans as being their own downfall, with God in the position of savior</note> that he may forgive,</l> 
                        <l>And <ref target="a009" corresp="n009">dye himself</ref><note xml:id="n009" target="a009" >Emphasis on God as giving -- God creates earth and man, then dies for man</note> before Mankind could live?</l> 
                        <l>And what still are we, when our <ref target="a010" corresp="n010">King</ref><note xml:id="n010" target="a010" >God as sovereign ruler--a very literal translation of the "divine ruler" connotation of king(?)</note> in vain</l>
                        <l>Begs his lost Rebels to be Friends again?</l> 
                        <l>What flouds of Love proceed from Heaven's smile,</l>
                        <l>At once to pardon and to reconcile?</l>
                        <l>What God himself hath made he cannot hate,</l>
                        <l>For 'tis one act <ref target="a011" corresp="n011">to Love and to Create:</ref><note xml:id="n011" target="a011" >Characterization of God as ultimately giving--despite Philips repeating how humanity is damning itself, God is never portrayed as upset, only understanding</note></l> 
                        <l>And he's too perfect full of Majesty,</l>
                        <l>To need additions from <ref target="a012" corresp="n012">our Misery.</ref><note xml:id="n012" target="a012" >Establishes human state as Misery (also, line 9, "since Man in Misery was hurl'd")</note></l> 
                        <l>He hath <ref target="a012" corresp="n013">a Father's, not a Tyrant's,</ref><note xml:id="n013" target="a013" > References God as "our King" and "a Father", but removes negative connotations (not a "Tyrant")-- portrays God as being in a natural, uncontested position of power</note> joy;</l> 
                        <l>Shews more his Pow'r to save, than to destroy.</l>
                        <l>Did there ten thousand Worlds to ruine fall,</l>
                        <l>One God could save, one Christ redeem them all.</l>
                        <l>Be silent then, ye narrow Soulds, take heed</l>
                        <l>Left you restrain the <ref target="a014" corresp="n014">Mercy</ref><note xml:id="n014" target="a014">Again, humans as self-sabotaging -- they will need "Mercy", but might prevent themselves from achieving it by their own actions against God</note> you will need.</l> 
                        <l>But, O my Soul, from these be different,</l> 	
                        <l>Imitate thou a nobler <ref target="a015" corresp="n015">Precedent:</ref><note xml:id="n015" target="a015" >precedent: an earlier event or action that is regarded as an example or guide to be considered in subsequent similar circumstances (Dictionary.com)</note>	</l> 
                        <l>As God with open Arms the World does woo,</l>
                        <l>Learn thou like God to be enlarged too;</l>
                        <l>As he begs thy <ref target="a016" corresp="n016">consent to pardon thee,</ref><note n="n016" target="a016" >"consent" and "pardon" indicates procedure (plus line 1, "contract") -- that humans must consent to their own salvation</note></l> 
                        <l>Learn to submit unto <ref target="a017" corresp="n017">thy Enemy;</ref><note xml:id="n017" target="a017" >"thy Enemy" as God</note></l> 		                        
                        <l>As he stands ready thee to entertain,</l>		
                        <l>Be thou as forward to return again;</l>
                        <l>As he was Crucify'd for thee and <ref target="a018" corresp="n018">by thee</ref><note xml:id="n018" target="a018" >The speaker emphasizes that humans are their own downfall through their sin. Despite this, it was humanity's "sin" of disbelief and hate that led to the crucifition of Jesus, which in turn led to the pardoning of all human sin. In this instance, did humanity's sin prompt their own salvation? Is the speaker indicating that sin is so integrally human that God accounted for sin as the tool to provoking humanity's salvation through Jesus's murder?</note>		</l> 
                        <l xml:id="a019" corresp="n019">Crucifie thou what caus'd his Agony;</l> <note xml:id="n019" target="a019">Speaker ends with a suggestion to the audience--a "moral" poem, as it were</note>
                        <l>And like to him be mortify'd to sin,</l>
                        <l>Die to the World as he dy'd for it then.</l>
                    </lg>
                    
            <figure>    
                <graphic url="http://www.tei-c.org/logos/TEI-glow.png"/>
            </figure>
        </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
