<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Tim Schott ENEC 3130 Poem Annotation one 9/15/16-->
<poem>

<title> Of the vanity of all wordly creatures</title>

<author> Anne Bradstreet</author>

<stanza>
    <l>As he said vanity, so vain say I</l>
    <l>O vanity, O vain all under skie,</l>
    <l>Where is the man can say, lo, I have found</l>
    <l>On brittle earth, a consolation sound?</l>
    <l>What is't in honour, to be set on high?</l>
    <l>No, they like beasts, and sonnes of men shall die,</l>
    <l>And whilst they live, how oft doth turn their State?</l>
    <l>He's now a slave, that was a Prince of late.</l>
    <l>What is't in wealth, great treasures for to gain?</l>
    <l>No, that's but labour anxious, care and pain.</l>
    <l>He heaps up riches, and he heaps us sorrow,</l>
    <l>Its his to day, but who's his heire to morrow?</l>
    <l>What then? content in pleasures canst thou find?</l>
    <l>More vain then all, that's but to grasp the wind</l>
    <l>The sensuall senses for a time they please,</l>
    <l>Mean while the conscience rage, who shall appease?</l>
    <l>What is't in beauty? no, that's but a snare,</l>
    <l>They'r foul enough to day, that once was fair,</l>
    <l>What, Is't in flowring youth, or manly age?</l>
    <l>The first is prone to vice, the last to rage.</l>
    <l>Where is it then? in wisdome, learning, arts?</l>
    <l>Sure if on earth, it must be in those parts;</l>
    <l>Yet these, the wisest man of men did find,</l>
    <l>But vanity, vexation of the mind,</l>
    <l>And he that knows the most doth still bemoan,</l>
    <l>He knows not all, there there is to be known,</l>
    <l>What is it then? to do as Stoicks tell,</l>
    <l>Nor laugh, nor weep, let things go ill or well:</l>
    <l>Such stoicks are but stocks, such teaching vain:</l>
    <l>While man is man, he shall have ease or pain.</l>
    <l>If not in honour, beauty, age, nor treasure,</l>
    <l>Nor yet in learning, wisdome, youth nor pleasure,</l>
    <l>Where shall I cimbe, sound, seek, search or find,</l>
    <l>That <italics>summum Bonum</italics> <note>This phrase, coined by Cicero, 
        means "the highest good." It evidences the broad 
        extent of Bradstreet's classical
    knowledge (OED).</note>which may stay my mind?</l>
    <l>There is a path, no vultures eye hath seen.</l>
    <l>Where lions fierce, nor lions whelps hath been,</l>
    <l>Which leads unto that living Christall fount,</l>
    <l>Who drinks thereof, the world doth naught account.</l>
    <l>The depth, and sea, hath said its not in me,</l>    
    <l>With pearl and gold it shall not valued be:</l>
    <l>For <italics>Saphyre</italics>, <italics>Onix</italics>,<italics>Topas</italics>,
    who will change,</l>    
    <l>Its hid fro meyes of men, they count it strange,</l>
    <l>Death and destruction, the fame hath heard,</l>    
    <l>But where, and what it is, from heaven's declar'd</l>
    <l>It brings to honour, which shall not decay,</l>
    <l>It steeres with wealth, which time cann't wear away.</l>
    <l>It yeeldeth pleasures, farre beyond conceit,</l>
    <l>And truly beautifies without deceit.</l>
    <l>Nor strength nor widsome, nor fresh youth shall fade,</l>
    <l>Nor death shall see, but are immortal made,</l>
    <l>This pearl of price, this tree of life, this spring,</l>
    <l>Who is possessed of, shall reign a King,</l>
    <l>Nor change of state, nor cares shall ever see,</l>
    <l>But wear his Crown unto eternitie</l>
    <l>This satiates the soul, this stayes the mind,</l>
    <l>The rest's but vanity, and vain we find.</l>
    
</stanza>
    
</poem>